Guide to the Howard Zinn Papers TAM.542
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Howard Zinn Papers
1901-2010
1944-2010
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Zinn, Howard, 1922-2010
Kabat-Zinn, Myla
Zinn, Jeff
Howard Zinn Revocable Trust
TAM.542
85.5 Linear Feet in 83 record cartons, 1 manuscript box, 1 CD box, 1 oversize flat box, 1 oversize poster box and 1 flat file drawer.
1 websites in 1 archived website
Howard Zinn (1922-2010) was an award-winning historian, activist, playwright, teacher, public speaker and author of articles, essays and books including his best-selling A People's History of the United States. Praised for his moral courage and passion for social justice, Zinn influenced thousands of students during a teaching career of more than thirty years. Reaching the wider public through his books, plays, articles, lectures and in theatrical and television presentations of his Voices of A People's History and The People Speak, Zinn celebrated the lives of ordinary individuals engaged in the struggle for peace and justice, highlighting their often overlooked victories, and encouraging his audiences to engage as well. This collection provides a broad view of Howard Zinn's many activities and interests. Among his personal papers are school and military records, datebooks, biographical articles and interviews. Correspondence with a wide variety of individuals forms a large part of the collection. There are also published and unpublished writings; drafts, fragments and corrected typescripts; datebooks and notebooks; research materials and lecture notes; posters, photographs and transparencies; annotated books, publications of many kinds, and audio and video materials documenting lectures, interviews, discussions, readings and other public events in which Zinn took part. The collection also contains Zinn's archived website, first captured in March 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions. Archived websites are open to researchers without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Myla Kabat-Zinn, Jeff Zinn, and The Howard Zinn Revocable Trust in 2010; additional materials were donated in 2011 and 2019. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 2010.050, 2011.035, and 2019.064.
Arrangement
The Howard Zinn Papers are arranged into ten series, three of which are further arranged into subseries. Folders within each series and subseries are arranged alphabetically with several exceptions: appearances/speaking engagements are in chronological order as are audio-visual materials within each format and correspondence within specific sections.
The series arrangement of the collection is as follows:
Series I: Personal and Biographical Material, 1944-2010
Series II: Correspondence, 1962-2010
Series III: Writings, 1901-2009
Series IV: Appearances / Speaking Engagements. 1964-2008
Series V: Boston University, 1960-2003
Subseries VA: Teaching and Student Material
Subseries VB: Boston University Controversy
Series VI: Race and Civil Rights, 1932-2008
Series VII: Vietnam War, 1944-2001
Subseries VIIA: Vietnam War Material
Subseries VIIB: The Pentagon Papers
Series VIII: Subject Files, 1933-2010
Series IX: Books with Zinn Annotations, 1929-1997
Series X: Audio-Visual Material, 1957-2009
Subseries XA: Audio Cassettes
Subseries XB: Audio Compact Disks
Subseries XC: Audio Reel-to-Reel
Subseries XD: Video DVDs
Subseries XE: Video VHS
Subseries XF: Video, Other Formats
Historical/Biographical Note
Howard Zinn (1922-2010) was an award-winning historian, activist, playwright, teacher, public speaker and author of articles, essays and books including the best-selling A People's History of the United States. Praised for his moral courage and passion for social justice, Zinn influenced thousands of students during a teaching career of more than thirty years. Reaching the wider public through his books, plays, articles, lectures and in theatrical and television presentations of his Voices of A People's History and The People Speak, Zinn celebrated the lives of ordinary individuals engaged in the struggle for peace and justice, highlighting their often overlooked victories, and encouraging his audiences to engage as well.
Born on August 24, 1922, Howard Zinn was one of four sons of working-class Jewish immigrants Edward and Jennie (Rabinowitz) Zinn. Growing up in Brooklyn, he held after school and summer jobs from the age of fourteen, graduated from Thomas Jefferson High School, and worked as an apprentice ship fitter at the Brooklyn Navy Yard. In early 1943, he joined the Army Air Corps, attaining the rank of Second Lieutenant. He trained as a bombardier and flew both combat and humanitarian missions in Europe. In 1944 he married Roslyn Shechter and, after the war, they lived in public housing and began raising a family while he attended New York University on the GI Bill and worked at a variety of menial jobs. Earning an undergraduate degree from NYU in 1951, Zinn continued his education at Columbia University, completing his MA in 1952 and PhD in 1958. In 1960-1961, he was a post-doctoral fellow in East Asian Studies at Harvard University.
After part-time lecturing in history and political science (1953-1956) at Upsala College in New Jersey, Zinn accepted a position at Spelman College in Atlanta as Chairman of the Department of History and Social Sciences (1956). During his seven years at Spelman, an all-black women's college, he became deeply involved in the civil rights movement – mentoring student activists, participating in sit-ins and other actions, advising the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) and producing articles for publications such as The Nation and Harper's. His activism made him unpopular with the school's administration and, in 1963, he was dismissed. Forty-one years later, in 2005, Zinn was invited to give Spelman's commencement address and the school awarded him an honorary Doctor of Humane Letters.
In 1964 Zinn published two books focusing on the civil rights movement – SNCC: The New Abolitionists and The Southern Mystique—and also accepted a teaching position at Boston University.
His 24 years at BU were marked by overbooked classes and clashes with the administration, as well as teach-ins, strikes, debates, rallies and the writing of many articles, essays and books including two of particular note – Vietnam: The Logic of Withdrawal (1967), one of the first to strongly condemn US actions in Vietnam, and A People's History of the Unites States (1980), his most popular work. Noam Chomsky describes this as "his enduring masterpiece", a book that communicates Zinn's "fundamental message about the crucial role of the people who remain unknown in carrying forward the endless struggle for peace and justice…"
Howard Zinn retired from Boston University in 1988. His relatively early retirement allowed him to concentrate on speaking and writing and to continue participating in demonstrations, protests, strikes and acts of civil disobedience which, on some occasions, resulted in his arrest. He spoke out against capital punishment and for improved prison conditions, expressed strong concerns about the environment and nuclear issues, consistently criticized US foreign policy in Central America and elsewhere, and was strongly opposed to the invasion and occupation of Iraq.
In 2002, Harper Collins celebrated the sale of one million copies of A People's History of the United States with a New York City performance of readings based on the book. This was followed in 2004 by publication of Voices of a People's History of the United States in which Zinn and Anthony Arnove collected speeches, articles, essays, poetry and song lyrics by the individuals described in A People's History. Public performances of selections from Voices culminated in the production of a feature film, The People Speak, in 2009. The film features Zinn, along with well-known entertainers such as Matt Damon, Morgan Freeman, Bob Dylan, Bruce Springsteen, Viggo Mortensen, Marisa Tomei, Josh Brolin and Danny Glover. These performances, as well as references to Zinn in popular culture, including a mention in the 1997 film Good Will Hunting, significantly increased the number of his readers and viewers. In 2008, the nonprofit Zinn Education Project was established to provide teaching materials based on Zinn's work to educators at the secondary school level insuring that his views on history, politics and social justice would continue to be introduced to young audiences.
Howard Zinn died on January 27, 2010. He and his wife Roslyn, who died in 2008, had two children, Myla Kabat-Zinn and Jeff Zinn, and five grandchildren. Zinn's life and work are described in his 1995 autobiography You Can't Be Neutral on a Moving Train which was released in 2004 as a documentary film of the same name.
Custodial History
Websites are selected by curators and captured through the use of Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website.
The archived website was migrated from the California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service to the Internet Archive's Archive-It Service in November 2015. The link to California Digital Library was removed in October 2017.
Related Archival Material
Howard Zinn Papers, 1956-1970
The Wisconsin Historical Society holds a small manuscript collection acquired from Howard Zinn (1966, 1980) focusing primarily on Zinn's research on the civil rights movement and his personal involvement with the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) during the 1960s. The Wisconsin Historical Society finding aid may be accessed at http://digital.library.wisc.edu/1711.dl/wiarchives.uw-whs-mss00588
Scope and Content Note
This collection provides a broad view of Howard Zinn's many activities and interests. Among his personal papers are school and military records, datebooks, biographical articles and interviews. Correspondence with a wide variety of individuals forms a large part of the collection. There are also published and unpublished writings; drafts, fragments and corrected typescripts; datebooks and notebooks; research materials and lecture notes; posters, photographs and transparencies; annotated books, publications of many kinds, and audio and video materials documenting lectures, interviews, discussions, readings and other public events in which Zinn took part.
Correspondence is found in almost every series. The correspondence included in "Series II: Correspondence" is the most varied, containing letters, emails, postcards and related materials that Zinn had consolidated and arranged by year. Letters in "Series I: Personal and Biographical Material" involve family and close friends, and are personal in nature, while within "Series III: Writings", much of the correspondence reflects communication with publishers, editors, actors and others involved in his various projects. Zinn associated the remaining correspondence with specific topics, individuals, events or issues being addressed and that arrangement has been maintained.
Howard Zinn's extensive travels outside the United States are reflected in many parts of the collection. In addition to material in "Series VII: Vietnam War" describing his visits to Vietnam, Paris and Japan, there are a number of folders in "Series VIII: Subject Files" containing publications, clippings and notes from his 1982 visit to South Africa as well as a copy of the speech he gave in Cape Town in "Series III: Writings." He made a number of trips to Paris (1974, 1978, 1984) where he was a visiting professor at the University of Paris (Vincennes and Institut Charles Civiq) and to Italy as a Fulbright Distinguished Professor at the University of Bologna (1995). Personal correspondence and memorabilia from these and other European travels, as well as from his South African visit and several trips to Cuba, may be found in "Series I: Personal and Biographical Material."
There are many articles and newspaper clippings throughout the collection. It should be noted that he often clipped only the portions of articles that interested him, sometimes saving an initial section and not the continuation. The name of the publication and date of the article were not always saved.
The collection also contains Zinn's archived website, first captured in March 2009. In addition to a biography and bibliography, the site contains print interviews, essays and commentary, audio and video, and information about The People Speak, the documentary based on the live performances of Howard Zinn and Anthony Arnove's Voices of a People's History of the United States.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact special.collections@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes JavaScript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
Separated Materials
A number of books from Howard Zinn's personal library were acquired with his papers and many of them were transferred to the Tamiment Library. (The more heavily annotated books were retained with the papers - see Series IX.)
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to repository email.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Bibliography
Robert Cohen, "When Assessing Zinn, Listen to the Voices of Teachers and Students," in History News Network (George Mason University, January 17, 2013) is based on correspondence housed in the Howard Zinn Papers. (@http://hnn.us/articles/when-assessing-zinn-listen-voices-teachers-and-students)
Printed ephemera.; Audiovisual materials.; Posters.; Notes.; Photographs.; Legal documents.; Historians -- United States; Clippings (information artifacts); Transparencies.; Civil disobedience -- United States.; Civil rights.; Draft resisters.; Trials (Political crimes and offenses) -- United States.; Correspondence.; Afghan War, 2001-; Notebooks.; Pamphlets.; Speeches.; Newspapers.; Economics.; Reviews (document genre); Plays (performed works); Essays.; Articles.; Boston (Mass.); War resistance movements -- United States.; Terrorism.; Middle East.; Anti-war demonstrations.; Peace movements.; Iraq War, 2003-2011; Race relations in the United States.; Prisoners -- Correspondence.; China.; Antinuclear movement -- United States.; Interviews.; Appointment books.; Scripts (documents); Research notes.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Protest movements -- United States.; Prisons -- United States; Academic freedom -- United States; United States -- History; Marx, Karl, 1818-1883; United States. Central Intelligence Agency; American Association of University Professors; American Civil Liberties Union; Abu-Jamal, Mumia; Boudin, Kathy; Ellsberg, Daniel.; Walker, Alice, 1944-; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Piven, Frances Fox; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994; Berrigan, Daniel; Silber, John, 1926-; Vonnegut, Kurt; Ahmad, Eqbal; Lynd, Staughton.; Chomsky, Noam; Berrigan, Philip; Kabat-Zinn, Myla; Zinn, Jeff; Howard Zinn Revocable Trust
- Series I: Personal and Biographical Material, 1944-2010; 445285
  Scope and Content Note
  The initial series in this collection contains a variety of personal materials as well as biographical articles and interviews. Among its highlights are school and military records, photographs, datebooks (1967-2008) and trip memorabilia.
  Personal correspondence includes letters from family members and friends; Daniel and Philip Berrigan, Kurt Vonnegut and Alice Walker are among the more well-known. In addition, there is correspondence and related material that describes Zinn's dismissal from Spelman College as well as letters of support and good wishes on his retirement from Boston University. One folder within this series contains recipes that had been clipped by Zinn and were found here and there within the collection.
  Several folders contain portions of the Federal Bureau of Investigation file maintained on Howard Zinn beginning in 1949 (File # 100-30217). In July 2010 the FBI released the file; it may be accessed in two sections at http://www.archive.org/details/Howard.Zinn_FBI.file_pt.1 and http://www.archive.org/details/Howard_Zinns_FBI_file_pdf_2_and_3.
  - Address Book, undated; cuid15272; 445286 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Arrests and Testimony, 1970, undated; cuid15273; 445287 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Awards and Recognition: Eugene V. Debs Award, 1998; cuid15274; 445288 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Awards and Recognition: Lannan Literary Awards, 1997-1998; cuid15275; 445289 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Awards and Recognition: Thomas Merton Award, 1991; cuid15276; 445290 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Awards and Recognition: Upton Sinclair Award, 1999; cuid15277; 445291 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Awards and Recognition: Various, 1987-2010; cuid15278; 445292 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Biographical Articles (Zinn, by others), 1968-2007, undated; cuid15279; 445293 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Biographical Data, 1980; cuid15280; 445294 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Personal (includes letters from Robert J. Lifton and from Noam Chomsky), 1964-1968; cuid15281; 445295 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Personal, 1974-1989; cuid15282; 445296 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Personal (includes letter from William Sloane Coffin), 1990-1999; cuid15283; 445297 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Personal (includes e-mail from Daniel Ellsberg), 2000-2009; cuid15284; 445298 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Personal (includes letters from Staughton Lynd), undated; cuid15285; 445299 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Personal - Berrigan, Dan and Phil Berrigan (also Elizabeth McAlister), 1968-2003, undated; cuid15286; 445300 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Personal - Carlsson-Paige, Nancy (mother of Matt Damon), 1998, 2006-2007; cuid15287; 451355 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: Personal - Cook, Samuel DuBois, 1965-1966, 2005; cuid15288; 445301 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Personal - Oladele, Jeanne Jackson (many observations of Nigerian coup and civil war; several essays included), 1965-1968, 1975; cuid15289; 445314 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence: Personal - Oladele, Jeanne Jackson (Nigerian newspaper clippings sent to Zinn with correspondence), 1966-1968; cuid15290; 445302 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence: Personal - Trips, Bologna (Italy), 1995; cuid15291; 445303 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence: Personal - Trips, Japan, [Jun 1966]; cuid15292; 445304 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence: Personal - Trips, Paris (includes letter from Jane Fonda), 1978; cuid15293; 445305 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence: Personal - Trips, Paris, 1984; cuid15294; 445306 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence: Personal - Trips, South Africa, 1982; cuid15295; 445307 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence: Personal - Vonnegut, Kurt, 1998-2006; cuid15296; 445308 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence: Personal - Walker, Alice (includes related material, mostly arranged by Zinn), 1962-1987, 1994, 1996, 2009; cuid15297; 445309 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Datebooks, 1967-1968; cuid15298; 445310 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Datebooks, 1970-1975; cuid15299; 445311 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Datebooks, 1975-1979; cuid15300; 445312 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Datebooks, 1979-1984; cuid15301; 445313 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Datebooks, 1984-1986; cuid15302; 445330 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Datebooks, 1986-1990; cuid15303; 445331 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Datebooks, 1990-1993; cuid15304; 445332 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Datebooks, 1994-1996; cuid15305; 445333 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Datebooks, 1997-1998; cuid15306; 445334 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Datebooks, 1999-2000; cuid15307; 445335 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Datebooks, 2001-2004; cuid15308; 445336 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Datebooks, 2004-2005; cuid15309; 445337 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Datebooks, 2007; cuid15310; 445338 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Datebooks, 2008; cuid15311; 449281 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Datebooks: Roslyn Zinn, 2008; cuid15312; 445339 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - "Diary of a Teacher", 1981; cuid15313; 445340 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Diplomas: Columbia University (MA and PhD), 1952, 1958; cuid15314; 445341 (Box 85, Folder 1)
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI) File, 1949-1953, 1967; cuid15315; 445342 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI) File, 1955-1971, 1978; cuid15316; 445343 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI) File, 1965-1972; cuid15317; 445344 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI) File, 1965-1974; cuid15318; 445345 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Fulbright Scholar: University of Bologna, Italy (includes letter from John Kerry), 1992-1995; cuid15319; 445346 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Interviews, 1968, 1973, 1988, 1992-2008, undated; cuid15320; 445347 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Journal Pages, [1975], undated; cuid15321; 445348 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Memorial Service: "A Celebration of the Life of Howard Zinn" - Poster (oversize), 2010; cuid15322; 445386 (Roll-storage OS Roll 1)
  - Memorial Service: "A Celebration of the Life of Howard Zinn" - Posters and Gary Huck Caricature, 2010; cuid15323; 445352 (Box 85, Folder 2)
  - Memorial Service: "A Celebration of Howard Zinn" - Program, Mar 27, 2010; cuid15324; 445351 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Military: American Veterans Committee - Suspension, 1950; cuid15325; 445353 (Box 3, Folder 2)